Trying to stay healthy can seem
like a full-time job sometimes.
Especially with all the conflicting
information that’s out there.
But, I’m here to make that job a little easier.
Welcome to the Nutrition Facts podcast,
I’m your host Dr. Michael Greger.
I knew next to nothing about cold plunges
when I started researching them and
honestly, they turned out to be
much more interesting than I thought.
In our first story we look at the effects
of cold water immersion on the
recovery of athletic performance.
In the last decade,
cold-water immersion
has emerged
as one of the most popular
post-exercise
recovery strategies
utilized among athletes
during training and competition.
This primarily stems
from the belief
that cold-water immersion
facilitates aspects
of recovery and regeneration,
thereby conferring
a potential training
and performance advantage.
But is it a friend, foe,
or just futile?
The cold truth...
is that local cryotherapy,
meaning like an ice pack,
does not appear
to diminish soreness
or accelerate
the recovery strength.
Local cryotherapy
does not seem to contribute
to the improvement
of delayed onset muscle soreness
or muscle weakness
associated with
exercise-induced muscle damage,
but what about cold plunges?
If you look at
the largest systematic review
and meta-analysis
of the effects of cold plunges
on the recovery
of physical performance,
compiling the results
of more than five dozen
randomized, controlled,
or crossover studies,
after cold-water immersion,
people felt less sore
after a workout,
at one hour later,
six hours later,
one day, two days,
and three days later,
but not after four days.
They also felt less fatigued,
particularly in the hour
or hours immediately afterwards.
And, after three days,
they reported feeling
more recovered
than those who hadn’t done
the cold plunges.
But were
they actually more recovered
using objective measures?
Endurance was significantly
improved an hour later,
but not after that.
Jump performance was impaired
six hours after the cold plunge
but was significantly improved
24 hours later.
If we put
all the studies together,
there may be a small benefit
favoring cold plunges,
but only about one in five
found statistically
significant benefit,
one found harm,
and the vast majority
found no significant effect.
Still, enough of the studies
leaned in the direction
of benefit to tip the scale.
In terms of sprint performance,
there was an initial
deterioration in performance,
but then none after that,
and a significant increase
in strength recovery
the next day.
This coincides with a lessening
of muscular damage indicators
the next day, lasting through
days two and three.
What are the best parameters
of cold plunges
in terms of timing,
temperature, and duration?
There really isn’t
a "gold standard,"
but the first systematic review
concluded that
cold-water immersion
at a temperature
between 11 and 15°C
for 11 15 minutes was best.
That’s like
in the 50s Fahrenheit.
However,
since that first review,
there’s been
a bunch more studies,
and the updated review
found that the water temperature
didn’t seem to matter,
whether severely cold at
5 to 9 degrees Celsius
(in the Fahrenheit 40s)
or that moderately cold
at 10 to 15°C,
but the immersion duration
did seem to matter.
Immersions lasting
less than ten minutes
presented better results
and plunging
for more than 16 minutes
didn’t seem to help at all.
And it’s better to immerse
immediately following exercise
rather than waiting.
Now, in most of these studies,
researchers used
passive recovery
in the control groups,
meaning people were randomized
to cold plunges
or to just, like, sit
in a chair for 20 minutes.
But who exercises intensely
and then just sits in a chair?
Many athletes use
active recovery
in the form
of a low-intensity "warm down"
to recover after exercise,
like walking around a bit
to keep the blood flowing,
getting rid of some
of that lactic acid buildup.
So, instead,
what about randomizing people
to cold-water immersion
versus normal active recovery?
That might be
a fairer comparison.
And in that case,
the cold plunge didn’t work.
It was no more effective
than active recovery.
Okay, but that’s just one study.
Let’s look at a meta-analysis
of all such studies
comparing the effects
of cold-water immersion
with other recovery modalities.
In terms of muscle soreness,
cold-water immersion
didn’t seem to work any better
than active recovery or any
of the other recovery methods,
including warm-water immersion.
Same for the recovery
of muscular power.
No significant difference
between cold plunging
and active recovery,
contrast water therapy,
which is like alternating
hot and cold,
warm-water immersion,
air cryotherapy,
like in a cryochamber,
massage,
or electrical stimulation.
If it’s all the same,
I think I might prefer
the massage to the plunge.
Same for the recovery of muscle
strength, no difference.
Immersing in cold water
did seem to beat out warm water
on perceived recovery, though,
but nothing else,
and it was the same with
flexibility, no difference,
and the same with measures
of muscle damage,
though electrifying your legs
did seem to work better
than the cold water.
The bottom line
is that all the recovery methods
seem to achieve about the same.
So, a cold plunge
may be better
than just sitting down
after intense exercise,
but there’s a wide range
of other practices
that appear to be
just as effective.
But any time doing something
beats out doing nothing,
you always have to ask if it
might just be a placebo effect.
You don’t know
if the perceived benefits
of cold plunges
are all in your head
until you put it to the test
with a placebo-controlled trial,
but how do you even do that?
We’ll find out, next.
Cold-water immersion
is a post-exercise modality
purported to enhance
physical recovery
following strenuous exercise,
and people certainly report
feeling less sore,
less fatigued,
and more recovered
after cold plunging,
but the vast majority
of cryotherapy studies
have been conducted using
a do-nothing control group,
like just sitting in a chair,
and have not taken
expectancy effect
or treatment belief
into account,
meaning maybe the cold plunge
only works
because people think it works.
In other words, could it
just be the placebo effect?
Practitioners didn’t
just feel better, though;
in some cases,
they performed better too,
but that also could be
a placebo effect.
Give athletes placebos,
and there aren’t only effects
on perceived exertion,
for example,
but on actual muscle power,
running speed,
and even heart rate.
Placebos, like sugar pills,
that are deceptively claimed
to be some
performance-enhancing drug,
actually enhance performance.
Or, give one set of people
a capsule of corn starch
and say it’s going
to make them run faster,
and another the same capsule
and tell them it’s going
to make them run slower,
and, you guessed it,
the it-will-make-you-faster
group ran faster,
and the it-will-make-you-slower
group ran slower.
Give people a sugar pill
and tell them
it’s a strong combination
of amino acids
with immediate effects
on strength,
and they magically leg
and bench press more,
until they’re informed
they were lied to
and learn
it was just a sugar pill,
and just like that,
their performance enhancement
disappeared.
You can even get
a dose-response effect.
When people were told
they were getting
about 300 mg of caffeine,
600 mg of caffeine,
or a placebo,
even though
everybody got placebos,
the ones who were told
they got the placebo did worse,
and there was increased power
in the lower
fake-caffeine group,
and even more in the higher
with all the fake-caffeinated
participants
even reporting
caffeine-related side effects.
Once people are told
they are taking a substance
that will enhance performance,
all sorts of things kick in:
belief, pain sensation,
expectancy, and arousal,
all of which
may impact performance.
No wonder there’s a gazillion
dollar sports supplement market
selling tons of drinks,
powders, and supplements.
They may work, but maybe not
any better than a sugar pill,
which would certainly be
a lot cheaper.
For cold-water immersion,
it’s difficult to administer
a true placebo,
but researchers cited a study
that did include
a placebo treatment,
and the effect
of cold-water immersion
was found to be no bigger
than the placebo effect.
There have actually been
five such studies to date.
Here’s the one
they were referring to.
Thirty guys performed
an acute high-intensity
interval training session,
comprised of four
30-second sprints,
immediately followed
by one of the following
three 15-minute
recovery conditions:
cold-water immersion
at 10.3°C +/- 0.2°C,
about 50°F,
a warm, near-body temperature
water immersion placebo,
or a warm, near-body temperature
water-immersion control group.
Uh, hold on.
What’s the difference
between the placebo group
and the control group?
In the placebo group,
the researchers squirted
something in the water
(actually just some soap)
and led the participants
to believe it had special
recovery enhancement properties.
This study demonstrated
that influencing one’s belief
in the efficacy
of warm-water immersion
as an ergogenic aid
in recovery
can account for an approximate
13 percent improvement
in muscle strength 48 hours
after high-intensity exercise;
so, it’s important for coaches
and sports scientists alike
to educate their athletes
on the benefits of recovery
and to also encourage belief
in the practice.
Wait, are they encouraging them
to lie to athletes?
Hey, if that lie is going
to increase performance
by 13 percent.
Here are the other four
placebo-controlled
cold-plunge studies.
Cold-water immersion offers
no functional or even
perceptual benefit
compared to a sham intervention
during an eight-week
resistance training program.
Here, researchers told people
in the control group
that their protein supplements
were tweaked
and that was enough
to completely eliminate
any significant effect,
and had the training program
gone longer,
they would expect
the cold-immersion group
to actually shrink
long-term gains in muscle mass,
or strength, or both.
The next was cold-water
immersion after a soccer match,
randomized to cold plunge,
passive rest recovery,
or a quote-unquote
"recovery" beverage,
which was just a placebo.
And both the cold plunge
and placebo were more effective
than the rest condition.
Doing something made people feel
better than doing nothing,
but the cold plunge did no
better than the fake beverage,
demonstrating that indeed
cold-water immersion reduces
muscle soreness,
but this beneficial effect
was a manifestation
of the placebo effect.
What about whole-body
cryotherapy--
like sitting in a cryochamber
at 100 below zero F (-73°C)--
versus cold plunge or placebo
after resistance exercise?
Neither cryotherapy intervention
was more effective
than the placebo treatment
at accelerating recovery,
neither was more effective
as a pill of cornstarch,
as long as you tell people
that cornstarch pill
is a branched-chain
amino acid supplement.
Oh my God, are athletes
that gullible?
No wonder these supplement
companies make off like bandits.
The majority of group
comparisons revealed
unclear, trivial, or unfavorable
effects of cryotherapy
compared to the placebo
intervention,
meaning in some ways,
the magical cornstarch pill
worked better,
contradicting much
of the previous literature,
but that’s because
much of the previous literature
compared cold-water immersion
to nothing,
just like sitting in a chair.
And finally,
recovery following a marathon:
a comparison
of cold-water immersion,
whole-body cryotherapy,
and a placebo control group
given a fake tart cherry
juice beverage.
Neither cold treatment,
whether wet or dry,
was more effective
than a placebo
at improving
functional recovery
or even perceptions of training
stress following a marathon.
In fact, the placebo worked
even better.
Cold water worked better
than the cryotherapy,
but they both did worse than
the fake fruit-flavored drink.
These findings lend
further evidence to suggest
that treatment belief
and the placebo effect
may be largely responsible
for the beneficial effects
of cryotherapy on recovery.
But what about the objective
drop in muscle damage indicators
after cold-water immersion?
It’s been reasoned
that reducing
muscle temperature
and blood flow
may dampen the local
inflammatory response
and thereby boost
post-exercise recovery.
What is striking is the
assumption that inflammation
needs to be dampened
or suppressed.
Isn’t inflammation
a crucial component
of the adaptive response
of skeletal muscle to training?
And cold plunges aren’t
actually anti-inflammatory.
Where did we even get
that idea from?
It was from studies
on lab animals
with induced
gross muscle injuries,
which isn’t exactly the same
as just exercising strenuously.
Okay, but there’s still
that reduced muscle damage,
even if doesn’t affect
inflammation
or muscle function recovery.
But doesn’t exercise-induced
muscle damage play a role
in skeletal muscle growth?
Might dampening the damage
be throwing cold water
on muscle growth?
We’ll find out next.
In my last video,
I talked about how
the benefits of cold plunges
appear to be due
to the placebo effect.
But cold-water immersion
isn’t just futile
but may be a foe when it comes
to our muscle mass.
A key take-home message is
that if the goal of training
is to build muscle mass
and strength,
regular cold plunges after
exercise may not be beneficial.
It all started
with this study in 2006,
showing that cold-water
immersion of muscles
may actually interfere
with regenerative processes
and retard rather than support
the desired improvements
of muscular performance.
Since then, independent
corroborating evidence
has continued to accumulate
that post-exercise cooling
diminishes muscle adaptations
to strength training,
leading to punny
click-bait titles like
"Cryotherapy: Are we freezing
the benefits of exercise?",
"Is the ice bath
finally melting?",
"The cold truth," "Cooling down
the use of cryotherapy."
Here’s a typical study showing
that cold plunges
substantially attenuate
long-term gains
in muscle mass and strength.
Twelve weeks
of strength training
with just typical
active recovery
led to a significant increase
in muscle mass in the quads,
but the same amount of training
with cold plunges
barely moved the needle.
And this manifested in
significantly less strength,
whether we’re talking
maximum leg-press strength,
knee extension,
isometric torque,
or rate of force development.
Note that smaller muscles
don’t necessarily lead
to less strength.
In this study,
the blunted muscle fiber growth
didn’t translate to
impaired strength development,
but post-exercise cold plunges
should be avoided
if you do actually want
bigger muscles.
But there are folks,
like long-distance runners,
who may not want
that extra bulk;
so, cold plunges may be a way
to keep their muscles smaller.
This is probably
the most rigorous study
involving measuring muscle mass
using the gold standard,
MRI imaging,
and actually taking muscle
biopsies before and after.
And, while both groups gained
muscle mass and strength
following training,
these gains were
significantly smaller
in the cold-water
immersion group,
compared with
the active recovery group.
And the cross-sectional area
of fast-twitch muscle fibers
also increased
only in the control group.
There have been all sorts
of published points
and counterpoints
about the cold-water dampening
effect on hypertrophy gains.
Here’s a systematic review
with meta-analysis
of all such studies.
A harmful effect of cold-water
immersion was verified
for every single
strength parameter measure:
one-rep maximum,
maximal isometric strength,
strength endurance,
and ballistic efforts
all reduced by cold plunges.
So, it appears useless
for endurance training
and deleterious
for strength training.
Why are people still doing it?
Here’s a 2024 meta-analysis,
and the title says it all:
Throwing cold water
on muscle growth.
This may be because
cold-water immersion
puts the chill
on muscle protein synthesis,
both in the hours immediately
following exercise
and during weeks
of strength training.
Another explanation
for cold-induced
reductions in strength
is that cold-water immersion
constricts the arteries
and causes a reduction
in blood flow
which is important for muscle
strength and development.
A 50 percent drop
in femoral blood flow,
compared to warmer water
or control.
Reductions in muscle blood flow
reduces the oxygen supply,
which plays a role in
the decreased muscle mass, too.
Cold plunges also blunt
the testosterone response.
So, the impaired testosterone
response may be another reason
for the attenuated strength
and muscle growth.
So, cold plunges following
resistance exercise sessions
should be discouraged,
but they are said not to impair
aerobic training.
That’s not always the case,
though,
as some studies show a reduction
in aerobic fitness as well.
This study found that muscle
warming was better than cooling,
thought due to the slowing
of glycogen resynthesis
in the cold.
Mean power output was
better preserved hours after
an all-out arm-cycling exercise.
The cold did worse than control,
and after the muscle heating,
there was hardly any decrease
in power output at all.
So, wait, should we instead
be taking a warm bath or sauna
after exercise
instead of an ice-water bath?
Regardless,
cryotherapy is apparently
not as cool as it seems.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see all of
the podcast episodes with descriptions that
include links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet, and How
Not to Age is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a science-based non-profit,
and everything on the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial, not selling anything.
Just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love
as a tribute to my grandmother whose own life was
saved with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.